Guide to the Todd-Bingham Memorabilia Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Todd-Bingham memorabilia collection
1832-1962
MS 496F
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
18
The collection consists of theater, concert, art exhibition and circus programs; pamphlets; periodicals; books; travel literature; dance cards; maps; sheet music; calling cards; engravings of paintings; advertising literature; and postcards assembled from the David Peck Todd, Mabel Loomis Todd, Loomis-Wilder Family, and Millicent Todd Bingham Papers in the Yale University Library. Taken together these items document three generations of the life of a cultivated family in the 19th and 20th centuries. Of exceptional interest is the collection of postcards, many of which date from ca. 1905-1918 and show European scenes in the pre-World War I era. The books include children's books (1855-1856), poetry, short stories, essays, and music.
Existence and Location of Copies
Additional information not yet available in the online version of the finding aid exists in the repository. Contact Manscripts and Archives for assistance.
Related Material
Related material: Loomis-Wilder Family Papers (MS 496A)
Related material: David Peck Todd Papers (MS 496B)
Related material: Mabel Loomis Todd Papers (MS 496C)
Related material: Millicent Todd Bingham Papers (MS 496D)
Related material: Todd-Bingham Picture Collection (MS 496E)
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from the papers of David Peck Todd, Mabel Loomis Todd, Loomis-Wilder Family, and Millicent Todd Bingham.
Arrangement
Arranged in three series: I. Programs, Pamphlets, and Printed Matter. II. Journals and Periodicals. III. Postcards.
Scope and Contents
The Todd-Bingham Memorabilia Collection consists of printed matter from the Todd-Bingham Collection (MS 496A-496F) that was not easily identified as belonging to any one person. For example, in the Memorabilia Collection there are a number of astronomy pamphlets, which may have been collected by either David Peck Todd or Millicent Todd Bingham. The same applies to the various art exhibit, drama, and music programs. Hence, in addition to that in the Memorabilia Collection, similar printed material can be found in the Loomis-Wilder Family Papers (MS 496A), the David Peck Todd Papers (MS 496B), the Mabel Loomis Todd Papers (MS 496C), and the Millicent Todd Bingham Papers (MS 496D).
The Memorabilia Collection, which ranges in date from 1832 to 1963, is divided into three series. Series I, consisting of twenty-five boxes, includes programs, pamphlets, and printed material. The items are arranged alphabetically according to subject. Of note are the many travel brochures of the United States and other parts of the world.
Series II, totalling seven boxes, contains journals, periodicals, and books. The journals and periodicals are arranged alphabetically by title. The books are arranged alphabetically by type, for instance music or children's books.
Six boxes of travel postcards compose Series III. The cards are arranged alphabetically by country and include scenes of the United States, Europe, Africa, and Asia. There is also a group of cards arranged alphabetically by subject.
In addition there are six oversize boxes and a folio which contain magazines, books, sheet music, and maps.
Art -- Exhibitions; Balls (Parties); Concert programs; Music -- 19th century; Popular culture; Theater programs; Travelers -- Europe; Africa -- Description and travel; Asia -- Description and travel; Europe -- Description and travel; United States -- Civilization; Postcards; Visiting cards; Bingham, Millicent Todd, 1880-1968; Todd, David P. (David Peck), 1855-1939; Todd, Mabel Loomis, 1856-1932; Loomis family; Wilder family
- Programs, Pamphlets & Printed Material, Series I
  - Academic programs, 1870-1898, 1900-1916, 1920-1961, undated (Box 1, Folder 1-5)
  - Advertisements, Circa 1869-1903, n. d. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Agriculture pamphlets, 1889-1922, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Amusement park program, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Anthropology pamphlets, 1884-1963, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Archaeology pamphlets
    - 1894-1897 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - 1911-1931, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Architecture pamphlets, 1892-1932, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Art exhibition programs
    - 1863-1906, 1908-1930 (Box 2, Folder 13-15)
    - 1933-1963, undated (Box 3, Folder 16-17)
  - Art pamphlets, 1887-1892 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Astronomy pamphlets
    - 1846-1890, 1894-1898 (Box 3, Folder 19-21)
    - 1899-1920, 1923-1932, 1958-1968, undated (Box 4, Folder 22-26)
  - Ballet and dance programs, 1899-1959 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Biographical and memorial pamphlets
    - A - D, 1875-1925 (Box 5, Folder 28)
    - F - H, 1879-1966, undated (Box 5, Folder 29)
    - J - M, 1827-1967, undated (Box 5, Folder 30)
    - P - T, 1874-1960, undated (Box 5, Folder 31)
    - V - W, 1836-1940 (Box 6, Folder 32)
  - Botany pamphlets, 1891-1962, undated (Box 6, Folder 33)
  - Calendars
    - 1886-1913 (Box 6, Folder 34-35)
    - 1914-1943, 1951-1965, undated (Box 7, Folder 36-37)
  - Calling cards, undated (Box 7, Folder 38)
  - Ceremonial programs, 1906-1965 (Box 7, Folder 39)
  - Chemistry pamphlets, 1889-1925 (Box 7, Folder 40)
  - Church programs, 1876-1961 (Box 7, Folder 41)
  - Circus program, 1853 (Box 7, Folder 42)
  - Clubs and conferences
    - 1883-1917 (Box 7, Folder 43)
    - 1919-1950, 1953-1967, undated (Box 8, Folder 44-47)
  - College and university pamphlets, 1872-1902, 1905-1931, undated (Box 9, Folder 48-49)
  - Community celebration programs, 1875-1961, undated (Box 9, Folder 50)
  - Dedication programs, 1870-1968 (Box 9, Folder 51)
  - Drama programs
    - 1856-1889 (Box 9, Folder 52)
    - 1890-1912, 1914-1917 (Box 10, Folder 53-59)
    - 1922-1966, undated (Box 11, Folder 60-61)
  - Economics pamphlets, 1863-1918, 1924-1949, undated (Box 11, Folder 62-63)
  - Education pamphlets, 1853-1895, 1897-1966 (Box 11, Folder 64-65)
  - Engineering pamphlets, 1893-1922 (Box 12, Folder 66)
  - Etiquette pamphlets, 1876-1895 (Box 12, Folder 67)
  - Exhibition programs, 1871-1950 (Box 12, Folder 68-69)
  - Film programs, 1904, circa 1938 (Box 12, Folder 70)
  - Geography pamphlets, 1893-1965, undated (Box 12, Folder 71-72)
  - Geology pamphlets, 1877-1940, undated (Box 13, Folder 73-74)
  - History pamphlets
    - 1832-1880, 1882-1898 (Box 13, Folder 75-76)
    - 1901-1943, 1949-1955, undated (Box 14, Folder 77-78)
  - Lecture programs, 1884-1962, undated (Box 14, Folder 79)
  - Letters, printed, 1844-1943 (Box 14, Folder 80)
  - Library and museum pamphlets, 1893-1955, undated (Box 14, Folder 81)
  - Literary pamphlets, 1847-1937, 1945-1966, undated (Box 15, Folder 82-83)
  - Mathematics pamphlets, 1885-1926 (Box 15, Folder 84)
  - Medical pamphlets, 1852-1931 (Box 15, Folder 84a)
  - Menus, 1886-1930, undated (Box 15, Folder 85)
  - Meteorology pamphlets, 1882-1938, undated (Box 15, Folder 86)
  - Music programs
    - 1857-1877, 1880-1904 (Box 16, Folder 87-96)
    - 1905-1919 (Box 17, Folder 97-105)
    - 1920-1932, 1948-1959, 1961-1968, undated (Box 18, Folder 106-113)
    - Boston Symphony Orchestra, 1889-1908, 1948 (Box 18, Folder 114)
    - Libretti, 1874-1911 (Box 19, Folder 115)
  - Nutrition pamphlets, 1895, 1905, undated (Box 19, Folder 116)
  - Physics pamphlets, 1906-1928, undated (Box 19, Folder 116a)
  - Political pamphlets, 1890-1919, 1924-1950, undated (Box 19, Folder 117-118)
  - Psychical research pamphlets, 1887 (Box 19, Folder 119)
  - Religious pamphlets
    - 1818-1887 (Box 19, Folder 120)
    - 1888-1897, 1900-1963, undated (Box 20, Folder 121-123)
  - Sales catalogues, 1854-1924, undated (Box 20, Folder 124)
  - Science, general pamphlets, 1878-1935 (Box 21, Folder 125)
  - Sociology pamphlets, 1892 (Box 21, Folder 126)
  - Sports pamphlet, 1906 (Box 21, Folder 127)
  - Sports programs, 1881-1930 (Box 21, Folder 128)
  - Technology and machinery pamphlets, 1850-1908, 1910-1962, undated (Box 21, Folder 129-130)
  - Tickets, 1873-1925, undated (Box 21, Folder 131)
  - Travel
    General note
    See also: box 22, folder 140
    - Atlas of oceans, lakes, and rivers, 1912 (Box 21, Folder 132)
    - Algeria, undated (Box 22, Folder 133)
    - Arctic, 1907 (Box 22, Folder 134)
    - Atlantic Ocean, undated (Box 22, Folder 135)
    - Belgium, 1884 (Box 22, Folder 136)
    - Bermuda, Undated, circa 1905 (Box 22, Folder 137-138)
    - Canada, Circa 1892 (Box 22, Folder 139)
    - China and Japan, 1898, 1901 (Box 22, Folder 140)
    - Europe, 1918 (Box 22, Folder 141)
    - France, 1900-1917 (Box 22, Folder 142)
    - Germany, 1909-1910, 1906 (Box 22, Folder 143-144)
    - Great Britain, 1863-1885 (Box 22, Folder 145)
    - Holland, Circa 1882 (Box 22, Folder 146)
    - Ireland, Circa 1885-1910 (Box 23, Folder 147-148)
    - Italy, Circa 1900 (Box 23, Folder 149)
    - Japan, Circa 1903, undated (Box 23, Folder 150-151)
    - Peru, undated (Box 23, Folder 152)
    - Singapore, 1889 (Box 23, Folder 153)
    - South Africa, undated (Box 23, Folder 154)
    - Sweden, 1911-1914 (Box 23, Folder 155)
    - Switzerland, undated (Box 23, Folder 156)
    - United States
      - California, undated (Box 24, Folder 157)
      - Colorado, 1893 (Box 24, Folder 158)
      - Florida, 1915, undated (Box 24, Folder 159)
      - Hawaii, undated (Box 24, Folder 160)
      - Maine, 1902-1911, 1950 (Box 24, Folder 161)
      - Massachusetts, 1882-1910, 1957, 1890-1907 (Box 24, Folder 162-163)
      - Missouri, undated (Box 24, Folder 164)
      - New Hampshire, undated (Box 24, Folder 165)
      - New York, 1879, 1924, undated, 1879 (Box 24, Folder 166-167)
      - Pennsylvania, undated (Box 24, Folder 168)
      - Virginia, 1912-1938 (Box 25, Folder 169)
      - Washington, D.C., undated (Box 25, Folder 170)
    - United States, general: pocket atlas; guides to national parks, Grand Canyon, and western states, 1890-1947 (Box 25, Folder 171)
    - Steamship and railroad guides, 1840-1909 (Box 25, Folder 172)
  - War pamphlets, 1881-1920 (Box 25, Folder 173)
  - Zoology pamphlets, 1870-1960, undated (Box 25, Folder 174)
  - Miscellaneous, 1895-1954, undated (Box 25, Folder 175)
- Journals, Periodicals & Books, Series II
  - Journals and Periodicals
    - A, 1868-1961 (Box 26, Folder 176)
    - B, 1878-1941, undated (Box 26, Folder 177)
    - C, 1893-1960 (Box 26, Folder 178)
    - E, 1873 (Box 26, Folder 179)
    - G, 1864-1965 (Box 26, Folder 180)
    - H, 1857-1889 (Box 26, Folder 181)
    - I, 1934 (Box 26, Folder 182)
    - J, 1911-1929 (Box 26, Folder 183)
    - L, 1897-1966 (Box 27, Folder 184)
    - M, 1822-1962 (Box 27, Folder 185)
    - N, 1967 (Box 27, Folder 186)
    - P, 1894-1925 (Box 27, Folder 187)
    - R, 1903-1930 (Box 27, Folder 188)
    - R, 1931-1934 (Box 27, Folder 189)
    - S, 1874-1948 (Box 28, Folder 190)
    - T, 1945-1947, undated (Box 28, Folder 191)
    - U, 1890 (Box 28, Folder 192)
    - W, 1872, 1907 (Box 28, Folder 193)
  - Books
    - Catalogue: The Buildings of the World's Columbian Exposition, 1892 (Box 28, Folder 194)
    - Children's books, 1855-1856, undated (Box 28, Folder 195)
    - Dictionaries, 1900-1918 (Box 28, Folder 196)
    - Miniature books, 1877. undated (Box 29, Folder 197)
    - Music books
      - Camina Yalensia, 1867 (Box 29, Folder 198)
      - A Collection of Tunes and Anthems for Public and Social Worship, 1868 (Box 29, Folder 199)
      - 82 Songs with Pianoforte Accompaniment by Franz Schubert, Circa 1882 (Box 29, Folder 200)
      - 48 Romances san paroles by Felix Mendelssohn-Bartholdy, Circa 1877 (Box 29, Folder 201)
      - La Marche à 1'étoile, 1899 (Box 29, Folder 202)
      - Our Flag: A Patriotic Cantata for School and Choir, 1896 (Box 29, Folder 203)
      - Schumann - Album, Circa 1879 (Box 30, Folder 204)
      - Songs and Duets by Mendelssohn, Circa 1882 (Box 30, Folder 205)
      - Songs of the Soldiers and Sailors, 1917 (Box 30, Folder 206)
      - Song Pictures, 1891 (Box 30, Folder 207)
    - Plays, 1845-1874, undated (Box 30, Folder 208)
    - Poetry
      - 1871-1902 (Box 30, Folder 209-210)
      - 1911-1967, undated (Box 31, Folder 211-212)
    - Short stories and essays, 1869-1925, undated (Box 31, Folder 213-215)
- Postcards, Series III
  - Africa - France (Box 32)
  - France - Germany (Box 33)
  - Germany - India (Box 34)
  - Ireland - Monaco (Box 35)
  - Netherlands - Quebec (Box 36)
  - Russia - Wisconsin (Box 37)
  - Airplanes - World War I
- Additional Material
  - OVERSIZE
    - Official Views of the World's Columbian Exposition, 1893 (Box 38)
    - Atlas der Himmelskunde, 1897 (Box 38)
    - Map of the Russian Empire, 1883 (Box 38)
    - Sight and Scenes of the World, 1893 (Box 38)
    - The Volcanoes of Japan, Circa 1890 (Box 38)
    - Delhi, Agra, and Rajpootana, Circa 1850 (Box 38)
    - Harper's Weekly, 1908 (Box 39)
    - Figaro Illustrè, 1906 (Box 39)
    - Werke Alter Meister, undated (Box 39)
    - Portraits of Hog Island Ferns, 1940 (Box 39)
    - Ornaments sur les monuments de 1'ancien art Russe, 1904 (Box 39)
    - Bound issues of The Home Magazine, 1888-1891 (Box 39)
    - The Masterpieces of German Art, parts 1-25, 1884 (Box 40)
    - L'Illustration, 1913 (Box 41)
    - Bound issues of L'Illustration, 1895
    - Sheet music (Box 42)
    - Bound volume of sheet music (Box 42)
    - Dance cards, 1868-1911 (Box 43)
  - FOLIO
    - Oriental illustration on rice paper, undated (Box 44)
    - Panama Canal plans, 1905 (Box 44)
    - Map illustrating the proposed system of standard time, 1883 (Box 44)
    - Pilot chart of the North Atlantic Ocean, 1912 (Box 44)
    - Photostat of Vassar diploma of Millicent Todd, 1902 (Box 44)
    - Issues of The Alpine American containing articles by Millicent Todd, 1919 (Box 44)
    - Handwritten proclamation to Millicent Todd Bingham thanking her for the Todd Wildlife Sanctuary, 1938 (Box 44)
    - Theater programs, 1881-1899 (Box 44)
    - Music programs, 1880-1900 (Box 44)
    - Circus programs, 1894, undated (Box 44)
    - Dedication program from the Hunt Library and the Rachel McMasters Miller Hunt Botanical Library, 1961 (Box 44)
    - Souvenir from the Columbian Exposition, 1893 (Box 44)
    - Atlas of the Northwest, Circa 1894 (Box 44)
    - "The 'Titanic' Disaster", 1912 (Box 44)